So friends, if you have also received a CKYC
message, that is, your account is
in any bank and you have received a
CKYC message from the bank
and in that message you have been
given a 14-digit number or
you may have also received an email if you
want to know and you are also worried about
why and how this message has come,
first of all let's talk about
what is CKYC and what does it mean, so let me
tell you that the full form of CKYC
is Central Know Your Customer, like
normally you go to your bank account to
complete your KYC, then there
you have to give your Aadhar card, PAN card photo
to complete your KYC or if you
open an account in any other bank, then you will have to
give documents for KYC there also,
you will have to do KYC for insurance also
or in mutual funds also, there also
you have to submit your KYC document, so
normally
where  Wherever it is required,
you have to provide documents for KYC, but
as soon as your CKYC is completed, that is,
whatever message you have received regarding
CKYC and the 14 digit
number given in it is your
CKYC number, now what will happen through that number, that is,
as soon as your CKYC is
completed, this CKYC is completed automatically by the banks,
that is, the message received by
you must have come from the bank, so the
CKYC is completed automatically,
now through that number,
wherever you need CKYC i.e. KYC, then there is
no need to provide separate documents, you just give that number, then
your KYC will be completed,
so the advantage of this is that now
wherever you need KYC i.e. KYC, then there is
no need for you to provide separate documents, you can provide the 14 digit
CKYC number you have received there, you can do so through that number  You
can complete your KYC through this and now after the new update,
you have got the option to download CKYC card here as well,
so
you can easily download your CKYC card as well,
I have made a video on this, if you
want you can watch that video,
you can download your card, so it
was a very simple process, in this way
if you have also
received a CKYC message or mail from the bank and a
14 digit number has been given in it then
you need not panic, this is your
CKYC message and Central Know Your
Customer is its full form and this
means that wherever you used to go for KYC, you used to give
different documents there,
now you do not need to give different documents,
you can
complete your KYC by directly giving the CKYC number